<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="funct.css" type="text/css"?>
<?xm-well_formed path="funct.dtd"?>
<slides>
  <addtranscript/>
  <footer>
    <a href="https://illinois.edu"
      alt="University of Illinois">
      <img src="../images/block-i.png"/>
    </a>
    Copyright &#169; 2020 University of Illinois
  </footer>

 <lang>en</lang>
  <title>The Sweet 16: Web Accessibility and Athletic Conferences</title>
  <person>
    <name>Jon Gunderson, Ph.D., CPWA</name>
    <desc>Coordinator of Accessible IT Group</desc>
    <desc>Division of Disability Resources and Educational Services (DRES)</desc>
    <desc>College of Applied Health Sciences</desc>
    <desc>University of Illinois at Urbana/Champaign</desc>
    <desc href="mailto:jongund@illinois.edu">jongund@illinois.edu</desc>
  </person>

  <conference>
    <name href="https://events.educause.edu/annual-conference">2020 EDUCAUSE Annual Conference</name>
    <desc>Online</desc>
    <desc>October 27th-29th, 2020</desc>
  </conference>

  <desc href="../">Presentations</desc>

  <stylesheet media="screen">../css/bootstrap.min.css</stylesheet>
  <stylesheet media="screen">../css/bootstrap-theme.min.css</stylesheet>
  <stylesheet media="screen">../css/bootstrap-accessibility.css</stylesheet>

  <stylesheet media="screen">../css/html-slides.css</stylesheet>

  <script>../js/jquery-2.1.1.min.js</script>
  <script>../js/bootstrap.min.js</script>
  <script>../js/bootstrap-accessibility.min.js</script>
  <script>../js/html-slides.js</script>

  <slide>
    <title>Goals</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li>Why Accessibility?</li>
        <li>Measuring Accessibility</li>
        <li>Summary data for 2020</li>
        <li>Who is in the Sweet 16</li>
        <li>Open source tools</li>
      </ul>
      <script type="text/javascript">
        slideShowURL()
      </script>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      This presentation is an invitation to learning about measuring web accessibility for people with disabilities and understanding the limitations of automated testing for accessibility.

      Most accessibility requirements cannot be tested automatically.

      Designers and developers need to understand accessibility requirements and build accessibility in to a website or web application during the design and development stage of a project.

      Just like adding curbcuts to sidewalks is much less expensive and more elegant when the sidewalks are initially built.

      The presentation concludes with the results of scanning over 1,700 websites from 151 educational institutions organized by basketball conferences.

      I will first give some background in why web accessibility is important.

      Second I will discuss the primary issues in measuring web accessibility.

      Third will look at summary data for groups of rules and for selected individual rules.

      Fourth, what everyone wants to know, where does my university rank in the accessibility scans I made in September of 2020.

      I will conclude with information on where you can get the open source tools used in this project.

      The slides for this presentation all use HTML markup and are publicly available on the web and a transcript of my voice is available on each slide, look for the Audio Transcript button.

      The "current slide URL" link on this page can be used to go to the actual HTML slides.

      So feel free to go to the link and follow along and explore the slides during the presentation.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Why Accessibility?</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li>Inclusive culture by reducing barriers.</li>
        <li>Universal Design in Learning (UDL) gives for all students more flexibility to learn and demonstrate their knowledge.</li>
        <li>Reduce or eliminate accommodations.</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Accessibility for people with disabilities is part of building an inclusive culture on your campus.
      Disability has traditionally not been included within diversity and inclusion initiatives in higher education.
      One issue is just counting students with disabilities, since students do not have to disclose their disability as part of their college application and the university is required not to ask.
      But disability is a part of the lives of approximately 1 out of every 10 students on campus.
      As information technology has become more apart of the educational experience, disability rights have been extended to include more than physical access buildings, but also to the virtual world of information technologies, just like curbcuts and ramps were eventually required to make sidewalks and buildings on campus accessible to students in wheelchairs back in the 1970s.
      Disability inclusion approaches based on Universal Design give all students more ways to learn course content, resulting in students taking less time to learn a topic and fewer questions to the instructor.
      For example in one study of an online math course using pre-recorded videos, half the class received the videos with captioning and half the class did not have captions.  The group with captions on the average spent 40% less time, approximately 45 hours saved, watching the videos with no significant difference in the grade distributions at the end of the course.
      Which videos would your rather watch?
      When instructional materials and online resources are accessible, students with disabilities do not need to request accommodations or spend time trying to explain to their instructor why their needs are different from other students.
      When students don't have to ask for accommodations, it makes them feel more included in the campus culture and gives them more time to focus on learning, rather than educating instructors on why they need something different and the delays in getting information in the format they need.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Disabilities Registered with DRES at Illinois</title>
    <contents>

      <div id="container" style="min-width: 310px; height: 400px; margin: 0 auto"></div>

      <details>
        <summary>Table View of the Data in Chart</summary>
        <table class="table table-striped">
          <caption>Disabilities Registered with DRES at Illinois</caption>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th class="text">Disability</th>
              <th class="num">2019</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Psychological</th>
              <td class="num">838</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">ADHD</th>
              <td class="num">641</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Systemic/Medical</th>
              <td class="num">362</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Physical Mobility</th>
              <td class="num">167</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Learning Disability</th>
              <td class="num">161</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Deaf/Hard of Hearing</th>
              <td class="num">49</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Blind/Visually Impaired</th>
              <td class="num">47</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Aquired Brain Injury</th>
              <td class="num">16</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Speech</th>
              <td class="num">2</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </details>

      <script src="../js/highcharts/code/highcharts.js"></script>
      <script src="../js/highcharts/code/modules/exporting.js"></script>

      <script type="text/javascript">

        $('#container').highcharts({
          chart: {
            type: 'column'
          },
          title: {
          text: 'Disability Served at Illinois: 2019-2020 Academic Year'
          },
          subtitle: {
            text: 'Source: DRES Annual Report'
          },
          xAxis: {
            categories: [
              'Psychological',
              'ADHD',
              'Systemic/Medical',
              'Physical Mobility',
              'Learning Disability',
              'Deaf/Hard of Hearing',
              'Blind/Visually Impaired',
              'Aquired Brain Injury',
              'Speech'
            ],
            crosshair: true
          },
          yAxis: {
            min: 0,
            max : 1000,
            tickAmount: 11,
            title: {
              text: 'Number of Students'
            }
          },
          plotOptions: {
            column: {
              pointPadding: 0,
              borderWidth: 0
            }
          },
          series: [{
            name: 'Students 2019',
            data: [838, 641, 362, 167, 161, 49, 47, 16, 2]
            }]
        });
      </script>

    </contents>
      <transcript>
        The chart in this slide shows the distribution of disabilities that are registered with disability services at Illinois during the 2019-2020 academic year.

        If you cannot see the chart or have difficulty reading charts there is an option to view a table of the data after the chart on the web page.

        I am pointing to the number of students in each category in the chart using the mouse:

        The chart shows:
        838 students with psychological diagnosis which effect learning in some way, example accommodations include taking tests in a safe environment or flexible schedules due to medication schedules or episodic situations.

        641 students with ADHD that may need coaching for prioritizing their work or distraction free testing accommodations.

        362 students with systemic or medical conditions that effect their daily living, for example a chronic disease like arthritis which may restrict mobility and reduced stamina.

        167 students with physical mobility impairments due to amputations or paralysis.

        161 students with learning disabilities that require the student to use different strategies to learn some types of materials, often requiring materials in electronic format for reading using speech.

        49 students who are Deaf or Hard-of-Hearing, these students rely on interpreters and text captioning for learning.

        47 students who are Blind or visually impaired who need print material in electronic formats or Braille with descriptions of images and graphics.

        16 students with acquired brain injury, including soldiers returning from overseas deployments, which often results in both learning disabilities and physiological issues which is helped by having multi-modal and flexible learning environments.

        2 students with impaired speech making it difficult for them to communicate to their instructors or fellow students.  In these cases disability staff can help develop communication strategies help the student to express their ideas in instructional settings and be a part of social groups with peers.

        While the traditional stereotype of disability is someone with vision, hearing or physical impairment, from the chart you can see that the vast majority of students registered have ADHD, learning disabilities or psychological conditions that effect their learning.

        The largest groups are often referred to as hidden disabilities, and so it is often difficult for people to understand their needs for materials in certain formats to support learning.

        It should be noted that typically only about a third of students with disabilities in higher education actually register for disability related accommodations.

        In a survey of all students at Illinois a few years ago, students who self identify as having a disability, only a third said they used disability services.

        Another third reported they did not need accommodations or could negotiate them on their own.

        The remaining third said they did not even know there were disability services available on campus.

        So you can see there are a lot of students in higher education and many students who can benefit from universal design in learning.
      </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Distribution of Disability by Age</title>
    <contents>
      <p><a href="https://www.census.gov/prod/2008pubs/p70-117.pdf">Americans With Disabilities: 2005</a></p>

      <div id="container" style="min-width: 310px; height: 400px; margin: 0 auto"></div>

      <script src="../js/highcharts/code/highcharts.js"></script>
      <script src="../js/highcharts/code/modules/exporting.js"></script>

      <script type="text/javascript">

        $('#container').highcharts({
          chart: {
            type: 'column'
          },
          title: {
          text: 'Disability Prevalence and the Need for Assistance by Age: 2005'
          },
          subtitle: {
            text: 'Source: Americans With Disabilities 2005'
          },
          xAxis: {
            categories: [
            'Under 15',
            '15-24',
            '25 to 44',
            '45 to 54',
            '55 to 64',
            '65 to 69',
            '70 to 74',
            '75 to 79',
            '80 and over'
            ],
            crosshair: true
          },
          yAxis: {
            min: 0,
            max : 100,
            tickAmount: 6,
            title: {
              text: 'Percent Population'
            }
          },
          tooltip: {
            headerFormat: "&lt;span style='font-size:10px'>{point.key}&lt;/span>&lt;table>",
            pointFormat: '&lt;tr>&lt;td style="color:{series.color};padding:0">{series.name}: &lt;/td>&lt;td style="padding:0">&lt;b>{point.y:.1f} percent&lt;/b>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>',
            footerFormat: '&lt;/table>',
            shared: true,
           useHTML: true
          },
          plotOptions: {
            column: {
              pointPadding: 0,
              borderWidth: 0
            }
          },
          series: [{
            name: 'Any disability',
            data: [8.8, 10.4, 11.4, 19.4, 30.1, 37.4, 43.8, 55.9, 71.0]

            }, {
            name: 'Severe disability',
            data: [3.6, 5.0, 7.5, 12.8, 20.8, 26.1, 27.6, 37.8, 56.2]

            }, {
            name: 'Needs assistance',
            data: [0.4, 1.3, 1.9, 3.4, 5.7, 7.6, 9.4, 16.1, 29.2]
          }]
        });
      </script>

      <details>
        <summary>Table View of the Data in Chart</summary>
        <table class="table table-striped">
          <caption>Disability Prevalence and the Need for Assistance by Age: 2005</caption>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th class="text">Age Range</th>
              <th class="num">Any Disability</th>
              <th class="num">Severe Disability</th>
              <th class="num">Needs Assistance</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Under 15</th>
              <td class="num">8.8%</td>
              <td class="num">3.6%</td>
              <td class="num">0.4%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">15 to 24</th>
              <td class="num">10.4%</td>
              <td class="num">5.0%</td>
              <td class="num">1.3%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">25 to 44</th>
              <td class="num">11.4%</td>
              <td class="num">7.5%</td>
              <td class="num">1.9%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">45 to 54</th>
              <td class="num">19.4%</td>
              <td class="num">12.8%</td>
              <td class="num">3.4%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">55 to 64</th>
              <td class="num">30.1%</td>
              <td class="num">20.8%</td>
              <td class="num">5.7%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">65 to 69</th>
              <td class="num">37.4%</td>
              <td class="num">26.1%</td>
              <td class="num">7.6%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">70 to 74</th>
              <td class="num">43.8%</td>
              <td class="num">27.6%</td>
              <td class="num">9.4%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">75 to 79</th>
              <td class="num">55.9%</td>
              <td class="num">37.8%</td>
              <td class="num">16.1%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">80 and over</th>
              <td class="num">71.0%</td>
              <td class="num">56.2%</td>
              <td class="num">29.2%</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </details>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
The chart in this side shows that disability becomes a pretty inclusive club as people age in the United States.

If you cannot see the chart or have difficulty reading charts there is an option to view a table of the data after the chart on the web page.

The chart shows the percentage of the population that has any disability, a severe disability and a disability that needs assistance for activities of daily living for nine different age ranges.

I am going to point to the rate of severe disability in the charts using the mouse:

3.6% for people under 15 years old.

5% for people 15 to 24 years old.

7.5% for people 25 to 44 years old.

12.6% for people 45 to 54 years old.

20.8% for people 55 to 64 years old.

26.1% for people 65 to 69 years old.

27.6% for people 70 to 74 years old.

37.8% for people 75 to 79 years old.

56.2% for people over 80.

By age 80, about half of people with severe disability need some type of daily assistance.

The ability to use the web will continue to be important as we age, so designing web pages to be accessible not only helps people with disabilities now, including our family and friends, but most likely we will also be helping ourselves as we age.
    </transcript>
  </slide>


  <slide>
    <title>Distribution of Types of Disabilities by Age Range</title>
    <style>
      table.table thead th {
        text-align: right;
      }
      table.table thead tr th:first-child {
        text-align: left;
      }
      table.table tbody td {
        text-align: right;
      }
    </style>
    <contents>

      <p>Data from the following chart and table is from the <a href="https://disabilitycompendium.org/sites/default/files/user-uploads/2017_AnnualReport_2017_FINAL.pdf">2017 Disability Statistics Annual Report</a> from the University of New Hampshire</p>

      <div id="container" style="min-width: 310px; height: 400px; margin: 0 auto"></div>

      <script src="../js/highcharts/code/highcharts.js"></script>
      <script src="../js/highcharts/code/modules/exporting.js"></script>

      <script type="text/javascript">

        $('#container').highcharts({
          chart: {
            type: 'column'
          },
          title: {
          text: 'Percentage of Types of Disability by Age: 2005'
          },
          subtitle: {
            text: 'Source: 2017 Disability Statistics Annual Report'
          },
          xAxis: {
            categories: [
            'Under 5',
            '5 to 17',
            '18 to 64',
            'Over 65'
            ],
            crosshair: true
          },
          yAxis: {
            min: 0,
            max : 25,
            tickAmount: 6,
            title: {
              text: 'Percent Population'
            }
          },
          tooltip: {
            headerFormat: "&lt;span style='font-size:10px'>{point.key}&lt;/span>&lt;table>",
            pointFormat: '&lt;tr>&lt;td style="color:{series.color};padding:0">{series.name}: &lt;/td>&lt;td style="padding:0">&lt;b>{point.y:.1f} percent&lt;/b>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>',
            footerFormat: '&lt;/table>',
            shared: true,
           useHTML: true
          },
          plotOptions: {
            column: {
              pointPadding: 0,
              borderWidth: 0
            }
          },
          series: [{
            name: 'Vision',
            data: [0.4, 0.9, 2.0, 6.6]

            }, {
            name: 'Hearing',
            data: [0.5, 0.6, 2.0, 14.6]

            }, {
            name: 'Mobility',
            data: [0.0, 0.6, 5.1, 22.5]
            }, {
            name: 'Cognitive',
            data:   [0.0, 4.2, 4.5, 8.9]
            }]
        });
      </script>

      <details>
        <summary>Table View of the Data in Chart</summary>

        <table class="table table-striped" aria-labelledby="h1_title">
          <caption>Percentage of Types of Disability by Age: 2005</caption>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th class="text">Disability</th>
              <th class="num">Under 5 years</th>
              <th class="num">Ages 5 to 17 years</th>
              <th class="num">Ages 18 to 64 years</th>
              <th class="num">Ages over 65</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Vision</th>
              <td class="num">0.4%</td>
              <td class="num">0.9%</td>
              <td class="num">2.0%</td>
              <td class="num">6.6%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Hearing</th>
              <td class="num">0.5%</td>
              <td class="num">0.6%</td>
              <td class="num">2.0%</td>
              <td class="num">14.6%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Mobility</th>
              <td class="num">-</td>
              <td class="num">0.6%</td>
              <td class="num">5.1%</td>
              <td class="num">22.5%</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Cognitive</th>
              <td class="num">-</td>
              <td class="num">4.2%</td>
              <td class="num">4.5%</td>
              <td class="num">8.9%</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </details>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      One of the questions many people new to accessibility ask is how many people have disabilities?

      How many people will be impacted if I make a website more accessible?

      While one slide cannot provide a detailed answer to these questions, the chart on this slide does provide some insights to the prevalence of four broad types of disability as we age: vision, hearing, mobility and cognitive.

      If you cannot see the chart or have difficulty reading charts there is an option to view a data table just after the chart on the web page.

      From the perspective of web design, it is easy for people to understand how someone with a visual impairment who has trouble seeing the computer screen or cannot see the screen at all would have trouble using a web page.

      For example, one of the best-known accessibility requirements is providing a text description or Alternative Text for each image in a web page, so that someone using a screen reader can understand the purpose of the image.

      I am going to point to bars in the chart with the mouse to highlight how the rate of visual impairments increases with age:

      0.4% for people less than 5 years old.

      0.9% for people from 5 to 17 years old.

      2% for people from 18 to 64 years old.

      6.6% of people over 65 years age.

      Multiply these percentages by 7 billion people and you can see that millions of people with visual impairments are affected by the design decisions of web developers and web development teams.

      People with hearing impairments have similar demographics as people with visual impairments.  I am going to point to bars in the chart with the mouse to highlight how the rate of hearing impairments increases with age:

      0.5% for people less than 5 years old.

      0.6% for people from 5 to 17 years old.

      2% for people from 18 to 64 years old.

      14.6% of people over 65 years of age.

      Comparing the hearing impairments to visual Impairments shows similar instances, until age 65.

      At 65 there are more than twice as many people with hearing impairments as visual impairments.

      The main design feature for people with hearing impairments is the availability of captions for videos.

      Captioning videos is a real winner for making the web more useful to everyone, since captions also benefit people who’s native language is different from the speakers on the video.

      For example, here at the University of Illinois we have many students from foreign countries including India and China.

      The use of video lectures has greatly increased in the past couple of years and in some courses the lectures are only available as a video, similar to the course you are taking now.

      While these students learn English before they come to the United States, for many of them the ability to read English is much better than their ability to listen to English, since there are often few opportunities to listen to native English speakers in other countries.

      In this case the captions will help them understand the lecture content much more easily.

      The captions can also help many students with learning disabilities that have trouble processing speech.

      The redundancy of the captions with the speech helps students to learn much more efficiently.

      Caption text can also be used by search engines to help people find specific topics of interest within a video.

      It is much easier to search for keywords in a video with closed captions, than videoes without closed captions.

      People with mobility impairments are not as common until people are over 18 years of age when about 5% of the population experiences a mobility impairment of some type and then increase to 22% for people over 65 years old.   Not all mobility impairments affect the ability to use computing and mobile technologies, but many do affect the ability of people to type on a keyboard, move and activate the button on a mouse, or point and tap their finger on a touch screen device.  In these cases, there is a need to make sure that web and mobile apps can be operated with assistive technologies like voice input or other devices that make it appear the person is typing from a keyboard or pointing on a touch screen.

      One of the most difficult to understand areas of making web pages accessible is for people with learning disabilities and cognitive impairments.

      I am going to point with the mouse to bars in the chart to show the prevalence of identified cognitive impairments:

      4.2% for people from 5 to 17 years old.

      4.5% for people from 18 to 64 years old.

      22.5% of people over 65 years of age.

      Current accessibility standards related specifically to cognitive impairments and learning disability are relatively few, but there is a wealth of information on how Universal Design in Learning techniques give students more options in learning course materials and demonstrating their knowledge of what they have learned.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Measuring Accessibility</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li>Standard: <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG">W3C Web Content Accessibility Guidelines</a></li>
        <li>Automated rules for testing WCAG conformance.</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      In measuring web accessibility it is important to understand two main concepts.
      The first is the standard for which accessibility will be measured against, the W3C web content accessibility guidelines.

      The second is the extent automated rules can be used to measure accessibility.

      Most WCAG accessibility requirements cannot be measured automatically.

      Care must be taken to not over interpret the meaning of automated test results, especially if the results to indicate few accessibility issues.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>W3C Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG)</title>
    <contents>

      <p>
        <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG" target="_specification">Web Content Accessibility Guidelines</a>
      </p>

      <h2>Important Features</h2>h2>
      <ul>
        <li>International accessibility standard, including the United States Federal Section 508 requirements for web accessibility.</li>
        <li>Technology agnostic, so understanding requires knowledge of features of specific technologies.</li>
        <li>Requirements identify the goals for accessibility, not the techniques.</li>
        <li>Techniques referenced by WCAG are <strong>not</strong> normative or comprehensive, but are deisgned to help people understand the requirement and feasibility of meeting the requirement.</li>
        <li>Supporting references:
          <ul>
            <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/quickref/" target="_specification">How to Meet WCAG requirements</a></li>
            <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/Understanding/" target="_specification">Understanding WCAG requirements</a></li>
            <li><a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20-TECHS" target="_specification">Techniques for WCAG</a></li>
          </ul>
        </li>
      </ul>

      <iframe src="https://www.w3.org/tr/wcag" width="99%" height="600px" title="W3C WCAG Guidelines"></iframe>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      The W3C Web Content Accessibility Guidelines or WCAG is the internationally recognized standard for the accessibility of web content, including the United States Federal Section 508 web accessibility requirements.

      Some important features to know about WCAG is that while it was inspired by the need to make HTML based documents and applications accessible, it was designed to be technology agnostic.

       WCAG can and is applied to a wider range of technologies, for example PDF documents and web application technologies like Adobe Flash and Microsoft Silverlight.

       WCAG is even being adapted to identify the features to make mobile applications accessible.

      The WCAG requirements identify the accessibility needs of people with disabilities to access online resources, with supporting references to techniques to help people learn how the needs can be met with a specific technology, like HTML or Adobe PDF.
      It is important to note the techniques are just advisory, they are incomplete and often missing common best practices.

      People looking for a design resource in the WCAG techniques reference will mostly be disappointed and frustrated, since the techniques are typically based on minimum requirements in code needed for what the working group considers sufficient implementation of a Success Criteria requirement.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Organization of WCAG</title>
    <style>
      .pour li:first-letter {
        font-size: 1.5em;
        font-weight: bold;
      }
      table.wcag thead th:first-child {
        min-width: 12em;
      }
      table.wcag tbody tr:nth-child(1) td ul,
      table.wcag tbody tr:nth-child(2) td ul {
        list-style: none;
        margin-left: 0;
        padding-left: 0;
      }

      ol.guidelines {
       margin: 0;
       padding: 0;
       list-style: none;
       counter-reset: section;
      }

      ol.guidelines li {
        font-weight: bold;
      }

      ol.guidelines li li {
        font-weight: normal;
        margin-left: 1em;
      }

      ol.guidelines li::before {
        counter-increment: section;
        content: counters(section, ".") " ";
      }
    </style>
    <contents>

      <table class="table table-striped wcag">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>WCAG Feature</th>
            <th>Description</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>4 Principles (POUR)</td>
            <td>
              <ul class="pour">
                <li>Perceivable</li>
                <li>Operable</li>
                <li>Understandable</li>
                <li>Robust</li>
              </ul>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>13 Guidelines</td>
            <td>
              <ol class="guidelines">
                <li>Perceivable
                  <ol class="guidelines">
                    <li>Text Alternatives</li>
                    <li>Time-based Media</li>
                    <li>Adaptable</li>
                    <li>Distinguishable</li>
                  </ol>
                </li>
                <li>Operable
                  <ol class="guidelines">
                    <li>Keyboard Accessible</li>
                    <li>Enough Time</li>
                    <li>Seizures</li>
                    <li>Navigable</li>
                    <li>Input Modalities (New in WCAG 2.1)</li>
                  </ol>
                </li>
                <li>Understandable
                  <ol class="guidelines">
                    <li>Readable</li>
                    <li>Predictable</li>
                    <li>Input Assistance</li>
                  </ol>
                </li>
                <li>Robost
                  <ol class="guidelines">
                    <li>Compatible</li>
                  </ol>
                </li>
              </ol>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>78 Success Criteria</td>
            <td>
              <ul>
                <li>Real requirements of WCAG.</li>
                <li>Three levels of importance:
                  <ul>
                    <li>A: Highest priority (29)</li>
                    <li>AA: Next highest (21)</li>
                    <li>AAA: Lowest priority (28)</li>
                  </ul>
                </li>
              </ul>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      We don’t have time to take a deep dive into WCAG, but I would like to give you a little more information into the organization of WCAG.

      At the top level are the 4 principles, Perceiving, Operable, Understanding and Robust.

      The first letters spell out the word POUR, so you often hear people talk about the POUR principles of accessibility.

      The principles are divided into 13 sub-categories called Guidelines which provide more specific labels for groups of success criteria.

      The Guidelines for Perceivable include:
        Text Alternatives.
        Time-based Media.
        Adaptable.
        Distinguishable.

      The Guidelines for Operable:
        Keyboard Accessible.
        Enough Time.
        Seizures.
        Navigable.
        and new WCAG 2.1 Input Modalities.

      The Guidelines for Readable:
        Readable.
        Predictable.
        and Input Assistance.

      There is only one Guideline for Robust:
        Compatible.

      I guess they wanted the “R” of Robust, instead of the “C” of Compatible to make the acronym “POUR”. Who wants to say “POUC”?

      The Success Criteria are the real requirements of WCAG.
      Each success criteria can have one of three priorities:
      Single A.
      Double A.
      Triple A.
      The Single A requirements have the highest priority for implementation and conformance.
      The Double AA requirements have the next highest priority for implementation and conformance.
      The Triple-A requirements have the lowest priority for implementation and conformance.

      The priority for a requirement is based on the consensus of the WCAG working group and take into account the importance and difficulty in implementation.

      The legal conformance standards for accessibility are based on the Single A and Double AA requirements.

      The priority is important when retrofitting accessibility into existing designs, since changes are difficult and expensive to make.

      Analogy is adding curb cuts to an already existing sidewalk, it requires using jack hammers and chisels to remove the existing concrete, before pouring the cement for the curbcut.

      On new sidewalks the curb cuts require little if any additional work and the same is true when designing a new web resource.

      When companies and organizations consider accessibility during the design phase of product development there is typically no or little cost in adding accessibility features, and accessibility testing can more easily integrated into the testing plan for the product or service.

      The priorities therefore guide companies and organizations who are new to accessibility requirements in identifying where to start their accessibility efforts.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Automated Rules</title>
    <contents>

      <table aria-labelledby="id1" class="table table-striped">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Result</th>
            <th>Description</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Passed</td>
            <td>The accessibility requirement has been met</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Violation</td>
            <td>Fails a required rule</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Warning</td>
            <td>Fails a reccomended rule</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Manual Check</td>
            <td>Human judgment is needed for verification of meeting an accessibility requirement</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Not Applicable</td>
            <td>No elements on the page applied to a rule</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      The automated rules used in this study could have one of five results.

      The first is passed, which means the accessibility requirement has been met.
      For example an IMG element has an ALT attribute.

      The second is a violation, which means a required accessibility feature is missing.
      For example a form control is missing a label.

      The third is a warning, which means a recommended accessibility feature is missing.
      For example an ALT text description should be less than 100 characters for the English language.

      The fourth is a manual check.  This means there is markup in the web page that indicates this rule might apply and it is up to the author to determine if an accessibility requirement applies and if it does, has the requirement been met.

      The fifth result is not applicable.  This means the markup was not found in the web page that would apply to this rule.

      For a typical website 35-40% of the rule results are passed, violations or warnings.  The rest require manual inspection and testing.

    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Data Collected</title>
    <contents>
      <h2>Purpose</h2>
      <ul>
        <li>Understand the strengths and weaknesses of automated testing.</li>
        <li>Importance of accessibility in the design and development.</li>
      </ul>

      <h2>Collection Details</h2>
      <ul>
        <li>Data collected in September 2020</li>
        <li>151 Universities</li>
        <li>2010 Websites, for each university the following websites were identified and evaluated:
          <ul>
            <li>University home pages</li>
            <li>College home pages</li>
            <li>Admissions and financial aid</li>
            <li>Disability services</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>129,287 pages</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      The purpose of this poster session is to help people understand the strengths and weaknesses of automated testing and that many WCAG requirements require manual checking, which means knowledge on the part of the designers and developers.

      The hope of this presentation is to encourage universities to start thinking about accessibility during the design stage of a website or application, where adding accessibility features is much easier and accessibility quality assurance can be included in the quality assurance process.

      The data was collected in September of 2020.

      Over 1,700 websites from 151 universities were analyzed for this presentation.

      The website came from university home pages, the home pages of major colleges, disability services, admissions and financial aid.

      A total of 129,287 web pages were analyzed.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Limitations of Data Collected</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li>Only public facing websites were evaluated.</li>
        <li>Only a small sample of websites from a university were analyzed.</li>
        <li>Web applications used for managing courses and providing interactive experiences were <strong>NOT</strong> included.</li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Only public facing websites were evaluated.

      Only a small sample of websites from a university were analyzed.

      Web applications used for managing courses and providing interactive experiences were not included, and typically have significant accessibility issues.

      Web applications need authentication and more complex testing strategies than simple spidering of web pages and analyzing mostly static content.

      Note that web applications like course management systems and other collaboration tools used in higher education are a challenge to meet WCAG accessibility requirements due to the level of interaction and user interface complexity.

    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Rule Category Results for 2020</title>
    <contents>

      <div id="container" style="min-width: 310px; height: 400px; margin: 0 auto"></div>

      <details>
        <summary>Table View of the Data in Chart</summary>
        <table class="table table-striped">
          <caption>Rule Category Results for 2020</caption>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th class="text">Category</th>
              <th class="num">Passed</th>
              <th class="num">Failed</th>
              <th class="num">Manual Check</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Landmarks</th>
              <td class="num">75.7</td>
              <td class="num">12.6</td>
              <td class="num">11.6</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Headings</th>
              <td class="num">87.5</td>
              <td class="num">12.5</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Styles/Content</th>
              <td class="num">20.6</td>
              <td class="num">2.9</td>
              <td class="num">76.5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Images</th>
              <td class="num">46.4</td>
              <td class="num">1.2</td>
              <td class="num">52.4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Links</th>
              <td class="num">23.1</td>
              <td class="num">12.4</td>
              <td class="num">64.4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Tables</th>
              <td class="num">36.7</td>
              <td class="num">26.8</td>
              <td class="num">36.5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Forms</th>
              <td class="num">52.8</td>
              <td class="num">4.9</td>
              <td class="num">42.3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Widgets/Scipts</th>
              <td class="num">69.6</td>
              <td class="num">3.6</td>
              <td class="num">26.8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Audio/Video</th>
              <td class="num">0.2</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
              <td class="num">99.8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Keyboard</th>
              <td class="num">31.2</td>
              <td class="num">1.0</td>
              <td class="num">67.8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Timing</th>
              <td class="num">-</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
              <td class="num">100.0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Site Navigation</th>
              <td class="num">-</td>
              <td class="num">0.3</td>
              <td class="num">99.7</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </details>

      <script src="../js/highcharts/code/highcharts.js"></script>
      <script src="../js/highcharts/code/modules/exporting.js"></script>

      <script type="text/javascript">

        $('#container').highcharts({
          colors: ['#F7B32B', '#E3170A', '#A9E5BB'],
          chart: {
            type: 'bar'
          },
          title: {
          text: 'Rule Category Results September 2020'
          },
          subtitle: {
            text: 'Source: 119,287 higher education web pages from 151 universities using FAE Auditor'
          },
          legend: {
              reversed: true
          },
          xAxis: {
            categories: [
            'Landmarks',
            'Headings',
            'Styles/Content',
            'Images',
            'Links',
            'Tables',
            'Forms',
            'Widgets/Scripts',
            'Audio/Video',
            'Keyboard',
            'Timing',
            'Site Navigation'
            ],
            crosshair: true
          },
          yAxis: {
            min: 0,
            max : 100,
            tickAmount: 6,
            title: {
              text: 'Percent Results'
            }
          },
          tooltip: {
            headerFormat: "&lt;span style='font-size:10px'>{point.key}&lt;/span>&lt;table>",
            pointFormat: '&lt;tr>&lt;td style="color:{series.color};padding:0">{series.name}: &lt;/td>&lt;td style="padding:0">&lt;b>{point.y:.1f} percent&lt;/b>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>',
            footerFormat: '&lt;/table>',
            shared: true,
           useHTML: true
          },
          plotOptions: {
            series: {
                stacking: 'normal'
            },
            column: {
              pointPadding: 0,
              borderWidth: 0
            }
          },
          series: [{
            name: 'Manual Check',
            data: [11.6, 0, 76.5, 52.4, 64.4, 36.5, 42.3, 26.8, 99.8, 67.7, 100, 99.7]
            }, {
            name: 'Fail',
            data: [12.6, 12.5, 2.9, 1.2, 12.4, 26.8, 4.9, 3.6, 0, 1.0, 0, 0.3]
            }, {
            name: 'Pass',
            data: [75.7, 87.5, 20.6, 46.4, 23.1, 36.7, 52.8, 69.6, 0.2, 31.2, 0, 0]
            }]
        });
      </script>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      This chart in this slide shows the results related to groups of rules organized by rule categories for all 129,287 pages analyzed.

      The set of rules used in this evaluation has at least one rule for each WCAG 2.0 level A and double A requirements.

      If you cannot see the chart or have difficulty reading charts there is an option to view a table of the data after the chart on the web page.

      The green portion of the bars indicate the percentage of rules that passed in the category of rules.

      The red portion of the bars indicate the percentage of rules that failed in the category of rules.

      The yellow portion of the bars indicate the percentage of manual checks for in the category of rules.

      You can see from the chart more than half of the rule results require manual checking and for the rules related to site navigation, timing and audio/video can only be checked through human inspection and understanding of the requirements.

      While the green portion dominates the red portion of the bars, it can be seen that there are significant failures for rules related to landmarks, headings, links and data tables.

      With data tables having the highest percentage of known accessibility issues.

      The widgets/scripts category is also misleading, since scripting accessibility issues require knowledge of Accessible Rich Internet Application or ARIA technologies to make sure the behaviors and sections of a website are properly defined.

      The passing and failing rules in the widget/script category are only looking for syntax errors, not if the ARIA was applied properly to describe the features and behaviors of the page.

      The weight of the manual checking rules related to scripting and keyboard support are critical for accessibility requirements to be met.

    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Selected Rule Results for 2020</title>
    <contents>

      <div id="container" style="min-width: 310px; height: 400px; margin: 0 auto"></div>

      <details>
        <summary>Table View of the Data in Chart</summary>
        <table class="table table-striped">
          <caption>Selected Rule Results for 2020</caption>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th class="text">Rule</th>
              <th class="num">Passed</th>
              <th class="num">Failed</th>
              <th class="num">Manual Check</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">All Content in Landmarks</th>
              <td class="num">70.3</td>
              <td class="num">29.7</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Main Landmark</th>
              <td class="num">78.4</td>
              <td class="num">21.6</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">H1 for Main Landmark</th>
              <td class="num">85.6</td>
              <td class="num">14.4</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Headings Nested</th>
              <td class="num">78.2</td>
              <td class="num">21.8</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Color Contrast Ratio</th>
              <td class="num">76.0</td>
              <td class="num">4.8</td>
              <td class="num">19.2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">ALT attribute for IMG element</th>
              <td class="num">92.8</td>
              <td class="num">7.2</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Unique link text</th>
              <td class="num">57.7</td>
              <td class="num">42.3</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Table has name</th>
              <td class="num">23.0</td>
              <td class="num">77.0</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Tables have headers</th>
              <td class="num">4.8</td>
              <td class="num">78.8</td>
              <td class="num">16.5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Form labels</th>
              <td class="num">89.3</td>
              <td class="num">10.7</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Grouping label for radios</th>
              <td class="num">51.4</td>
              <td class="num">48.6</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Skip to main link</th>
              <td class="num">70.8</td>
              <td class="num">4.4</td>
              <td class="num">24.8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Video captions</th>
              <td class="num">-</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
              <td class="num">100</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Audio must have alternative</th>
              <td class="num">-</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
              <td class="num">100</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">Control time limits</th>
              <td class="num">-</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
              <td class="num">100</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <th scope="row">At least two ways to find</th>
              <td class="num">-</td>
              <td class="num">-</td>
              <td class="num">100</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </details>

      <script src="../js/highcharts/code/highcharts.js"></script>
      <script src="../js/highcharts/code/modules/exporting.js"></script>

      <script type="text/javascript">

        $('#container').highcharts({
          colors: ['#F7B32B', '#E3170A', '#A9E5BB'],
          chart: {
            type: 'bar'
          },
          title: {
          text: 'Rule Category Results September 2020'
          },
          subtitle: {
            text: 'Source: 119,287 higher education web pages from 151 universities using FAE Auditor'
          },
          legend: {
              reversed: true
          },
          xAxis: {

            categories: [
              'All Content in Landmarks',
              'Main Landmark',
              'H1 for Main Landmark',
              'Headings Nested',
              'Color Contrast Ratio',
              'ALT attribute for IMG element',
              'Unique link text',
              'Table has name',
              'Tables have headers',
              'Form labels',
              'Grouping label for radios',
              'Skip to main link',
              'Video captions',
              'Audio must have alternative',
              'Control time limits',
              'At least two ways to find'
            ],
            crosshair: true
          },
          yAxis: {
            min: 0,
            max : 100,
            tickAmount: 6,
            title: {
              text: 'Percent Results'
            }
          },
          tooltip: {
            headerFormat: "&lt;span style='font-size:10px'>{point.key}&lt;/span>&lt;table>",
            pointFormat: '&lt;tr>&lt;td style="color:{series.color};padding:0">{series.name}: &lt;/td>&lt;td style="padding:0">&lt;b>{point.y:.1f} percent&lt;/b>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>',
            footerFormat: '&lt;/table>',
            shared: true,
           useHTML: true
          },
          plotOptions: {
            series: {
                stacking: 'normal'
            },
            column: {
              pointPadding: 0,
              borderWidth: 0
            }
          },
          series: [{
            name: 'Manual Check',
            data: [0, 0, 0, 0, 19.2, 0, 0, 0, 16.5, 0, 0, 24.8, 100, 100, 100, 100]
            }, {
            name: 'Fail',
            data: [29.7, 21.6, 14.4, 21.8, 4.8, 7.2, 42.3, 77.0, 78.8, 10.7, 48.6, 4.4, 0, 0, 0, 0]
            }, {
            name: 'Pass',
            data: [70.3, 78.4, 85.6, 78.2, 76.0, 92.8, 57.7, 23.0, 4.6, 89.3, 51.4, 70.8, 0, 0, 0, 0]
            }]
        });
      </script>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      This chart shows selected rule results with the associated passed, failed and manual check rules.

      If you cannot see the chart or have difficulty reading charts there is an option to view a table of the data after the chart on the web page.

      The rule All Content in Landmarks is an indication content is associated with named regions on the screen.  The high level of conformance for this rule may be deceptive since common HTML sectioning like, the header, footer, nav and aside elements automatically landmarks, usually in a way that supports accessibility, but in some cases their may be too many landmarks or content in a landmark that is not appropriate.

      The Main Landmark requires authors to specifically define a main landmark using the role attribute or the main element.  This is a better indicator of authors using accessibility in their design, because adding a main landmark is usually not done by accident.  The chart shows almost 80% of website are using the main landmarks.

      When a main landmark is present the H1 for Main Landmark rule is passed over 80% of the time.   This makes an H1 heading element, which is easy for screen reader users to navigate to, available on alot of pages.

      Properly nested headings passes at over 80% and is an indicator the author is  using HTML heading markup correctly, making it easier for screen reader users to navigate the sections of the website.

      Color Contrast Ratio is passing at less than 80%.  Color contrast ratio is critical for people with visual impairments and this indicates there is a significant portion of web page content that will not be accessible.  Notice this rule has a manual checking component which is much larger portion of the result than failure of this rule.  Manual check is required when text is placed on top of a background images, so the background not being a solid color value the contrast ratio cannot be computed.

      The use of ALT attribute on an IMG element is the poster child accessibility rule for accessibility and probably the most well known rule for accessibility, since it is pretty esay for most people to understand that for someone who cannot see the image they will need some type of description.  Even though this rule is passing more than 90% of the time, there are a significant number of images that do not have a description.

      The Unique link text rule is passing at less than 60% of the time.   The most common problem when people have links like "more" or "click here" which do not describe where the link will take the user.

      Data tables are a huge problem shown by the low compliance of the next two rules related to a providing an accessible name and headers to provide context to the content of the data cells.

      the rule for labeling form controls has steadily improved over the past 10 years to almost 90% compliance in this evaluation.  Ten years ago when I started these evaluations less that 50% of form controls had labels.  But this is such an important and easy requirement to implement it hard to understand why compliance is not higher.

      The use of grouping label for radio buttons using fieldset and legend elements is still an area of poor implementation, with just over 50% compliance.  The is definitely a need for form designers to learn more about creating accessible forms with accessible error feedback.

      The Skip to main link provides a means for keyboard only users to move directly to the main content of the page and is implemented in about 70% of the pages evaluated and is considered a basic accessibility feature.

      The last four rules in the chart related to videos having captions, audio must have an alternative, the ability of users to have time to respond to web pages with time outs and website navigation features all require manual checks.

      These features need to be addressed during the design of the website, because just like curbcuts in sidewalks they are expensive to retrofit into production websites.

    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>2020 Sweet 16 Universities</title>
    <contents>

      <p><a href="https://fae-auditor.disability.illinois.edu/group2/all/2018-bb-conf-2-2020-09-15/rc/">Data for all universities evaluated.</a></p>

      <div id="container" style="min-width: 310px; height: 400px; margin: 0 auto"></div>

        <table class="table table-striped">
          <caption>2020 Sweet 16 Universities</caption>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th class="num">Rank</th>
              <th class="text">University</th>
              <th class="num">Passed</th>
              <th class="num">Failed</th>
              <th class="num">Manual Check</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">1</td>
              <th class="text">Buffalo</th>
              <td class="num">54.3</td>
              <td class="num">1.5</td>
              <td class="num">44.2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">2</td>
              <th class="text">Missouri State</th>
              <td class="num">54.0</td>
              <td class="num">2.6</td>
              <td class="num">43.4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">3</td>
              <th class="text">Xavier</th>
              <td class="num">53.3</td>
              <td class="num">3.3</td>
              <td class="num">43.4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">4</td>
              <th class="text">Indiana</th>
              <td class="num">53.0</td>
              <td class="num">2.5</td>
              <td class="num">44.4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">5</td>
              <th class="text">Davidson College</th>
              <td class="num">52.8</td>
              <td class="num">2.9</td>
              <td class="num">44.3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">6</td>
              <th class="text">Nebraska</th>
              <td class="num">52.7</td>
              <td class="num">2.8</td>
              <td class="num">44.5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">7</td>
              <th class="text">Bowling Green</th>
              <td class="num">52.5</td>
              <td class="num">2.7</td>
              <td class="num">44.8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">8</td>
              <th class="text">Ohio</th>
              <td class="num">52.5</td>
              <td class="num">3.5</td>
              <td class="num">44.0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">9</td>
              <th class="text">Georgetown</th>
              <td class="num">52.1</td>
              <td class="num">3.9</td>
              <td class="num">44.0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">10</td>
              <th class="text">Utah Valley</th>
              <td class="num">51.9</td>
              <td class="num">3.2</td>
              <td class="num">45.0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">11</td>
              <th class="text">West Virginia</th>
              <td class="num">51.6</td>
              <td class="num">4.7</td>
              <td class="num">43.6</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">12</td>
              <th class="text">Illinois</th>
              <td class="num">51.2</td>
              <td class="num">3.4</td>
              <td class="num">45.4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">13</td>
              <th class="text">Wichita State</th>
              <td class="num">51.2</td>
              <td class="num">3.0</td>
              <td class="num">45.9</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">14</td>
              <th class="text">Virginia Tech</th>
              <td class="num">51.1</td>
              <td class="num">5.1</td>
              <td class="num">43.8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">15</td>
              <th class="text">Providence</th>
              <td class="num">50.7</td>
              <td class="num">3.1</td>
              <td class="num">46.2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">16 (tie)</td>
              <th class="text">Cornell</th>
              <td class="num">50.5</td>
              <td class="num">4.2</td>
              <td class="num">45.3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">16 (tie)</td>
              <th class="text">UC Santa Barbara</th>
              <td class="num">50.5</td>
              <td class="num">4.2</td>
              <td class="num">45.3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">18</td>
              <th class="text">Illinois State</th>
              <td class="num">50.3</td>
              <td class="num">3.3</td>
              <td class="num">46.4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">19</td>
              <th class="text">Colorado</th>
              <td class="num">50.2</td>
              <td class="num">4.3</td>
              <td class="num">45.6</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">20</td>
              <th class="text">North Carolina State</th>
              <td class="num">50.0</td>
              <td class="num">5.6</td>
              <td class="num">44.3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">21</td>
              <th class="text">UC Riverside</th>
              <td class="num">50.0</td>
              <td class="num">3.2</td>
              <td class="num">46.8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">22</td>
              <th class="text">Yale</th>
              <td class="num">49.9</td>
              <td class="num">4.5</td>
              <td class="num">45.6</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">23</td>
              <th class="text">Southern Mississippi</th>
              <td class="num">49.8</td>
              <td class="num">5.2</td>
              <td class="num">45.0</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">24</td>
              <th class="text">Oklahoma State</th>
              <td class="num">49.7</td>
              <td class="num">4.3</td>
              <td class="num">46.0</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>

      <script src="../js/highcharts/code/highcharts.js"></script>
      <script src="../js/highcharts/code/modules/exporting.js"></script>

      <script type="text/javascript">

        $('#container').highcharts({
          colors: ['#F7B32B', '#E3170A', '#A9E5BB'],
          chart: {
            type: 'column'
          },
          title: {
          text: 'Rule Category Results September 2020'
          },
          subtitle: {
            text: 'Source: 119,287 higher education web pages from 151 universities using FAE Auditor'
          },
          legend: {
              reversed: true
          },
          xAxis: {
            categories: [
              'Buffalo',
              'Missouri State',
              'Xavier',
              'Indiana',
              'Davidson College',
              'Nebraska',
              'Bowling Green',
              'Ohio',
              'Georgetown',
              'Utah Valley',
              'West Virgina',
              'Illinois',
              'Wichita State',
              'Viginia Tech',
              'Providence',
              'Cornell (tie)',
              'UC Santa Barbra (tie)',
              'Illinois State',
              'Colorado',
              'North Carolina State',
              'UC Riverside',
              'Yale',
              'Southern Mississippi',
              'Oklahoma State'
            ],
            crosshair: true
          },
          yAxis: {
            min: 0,
            max : 100,
            tickAmount: 6,
            title: {
              text: 'Percent Results'
            }
          },
          tooltip: {
            headerFormat: "&lt;span style='font-size:10px'>{point.key}&lt;/span>&lt;table>",
            pointFormat: '&lt;tr>&lt;td style="color:{series.color};padding:0">{series.name}: &lt;/td>&lt;td style="padding:0">&lt;b>{point.y:.1f} percent&lt;/b>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>',
            footerFormat: '&lt;/table>',
            shared: true,
           useHTML: true
          },
          plotOptions: {
            series: {
                stacking: 'normal'
            },
            column: {
              pointPadding: 0,
              borderWidth: 0
            }
          },
          series: [{
            name: 'Manual Check',
            data: [44.2, 43.2, 43.4, 44.4, 44.3, 44.5, 44.8, 44.0, 44.0, 45.0, 43.6, 45.4, 45.9, 43.8, 46.2, 45.3, 45.3, 46.4, 45.6, 44.3, 46.8, 45.6, 45.0, 46.0]
            }, {
            name: 'Fail',
            data: [1.5, 2.6, 3.3, 2.5, 2.9, 2.8, 2.7, 3.5, 3.9, 3.2, 4.7, 3.4, 3.0, 5.1, 3.1, 4.2, 4.2, 3.3, 4.3, 5.6, 3.2, 4.5, 5.2, 4.3]
            }, {
            name: 'Pass',
            data: [54.3, 54.0, 53.3, 53.0, 52.8, 52.7, 52.5, 52.5, 52.1, 51.9, 51.6, 51.2, 51.2, 51.1, 50.7, 50.5, 50.5, 50.3, 50.2, 50.0, 50.0, 49.9, 49.8, 49.7]
            }]
        });
      </script>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      The chart in this slide shows the accessibility ranking for the top 24 universities based on the highest percentage of rules passed for all the web pages evaluated for that university.

      If you cannot see the chart or have difficulty reading charts there is an option to view a table of the data after the chart on the web page.

      As you have learned earlier in this presentation there are a lot of caveats with these rankings do to the limited number of pages tested, the exclusion of web applications and the inherit nature of many accessibility requirements needing manual checks, but it is kind of a fun way to compare universities and engage in the natural rivalries between higher educational institutions to motivate people to dive deeper into the accessibility of their campus websites.

      The winner this year is the University of Buffalo.

      Congratulations!

      There is a link to look at all the results, so if you don't see your school in this chart you can look at the data for all 151 universities.

    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>2020 Conference Rankings</title>
    <contents>

      <p><a href="https://fae-auditor.disability.illinois.edu/group/all/2018-bb-conf-2-2020-09-15/rc/">Data for conferences evaluated.</a></p>

      <div id="container" style="min-width: 310px; height: 400px; margin: 0 auto"></div>

        <table class="table table-striped">
          <caption>2020 Conference Rankings</caption>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th class="num">Rank</th>
              <th class="text">Conference</th>
              <th class="num">Passed</th>
              <th class="num">Failed</th>
              <th class="num">Manual Check</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">1</td>
              <th class="text">Midamerican</th>
              <td class="num">48.4</td>
              <td class="num">5.0</td>
              <td class="num">46.6</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">2</td>
              <th class="text">No Conference</th>
              <td class="num">48.4</td>
              <td class="num">4.0</td>
              <td class="num">46.7</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">3</td>
              <th class="text">Big Ten</th>
              <td class="num">47.7</td>
              <td class="num">5.1</td>
              <td class="num">47.2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">4</td>
              <th class="text">Ivy League</th>
              <td class="num">47.5</td>
              <td class="num">6.0</td>
              <td class="num">46.5</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">5</td>
              <th class="text">Big East</th>
              <td class="num">46.8</td>
              <td class="num">5.0</td>
              <td class="num">48.3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">6</td>
              <th class="text">Atlantic 10</th>
              <td class="num">46.4</td>
              <td class="num">6.4</td>
              <td class="num">47.1</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">7</td>
              <th class="text">Big 12</th>
              <td class="num">46.1</td>
              <td class="num">5.6</td>
              <td class="num">48.2</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">8</td>
              <th class="text">Atlantic Coast</th>
              <td class="num">45.8</td>
              <td class="num">6.6</td>
              <td class="num">47.6</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">9</td>
              <th class="text">Missouri Valley</th>
              <td class="num">45.6</td>
              <td class="num">6.6</td>
              <td class="num">47.8</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">10</td>
              <th class="text">Pacific 12</th>
              <td class="num">45.4</td>
              <td class="num">7.3</td>
              <td class="num">47.3</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">11</td>
              <th class="text">Southeast</th>
              <td class="num">45.4</td>
              <td class="num">7.2</td>
              <td class="num">47.4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">12</td>
              <th class="text">Big West</th>
              <td class="num">45.3</td>
              <td class="num">6.0</td>
              <td class="num">48.7</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">13</td>
              <th class="text">Conference USA</th>
              <td class="num">44.4</td>
              <td class="num">7.2</td>
              <td class="num">48.4</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td scope="row" class="num">14</td>
              <th class="text">Western Athletic</th>
              <td class="num">43.5</td>
              <td class="num">6.4</td>
              <td class="num">50.1</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>

      <script src="../js/highcharts/code/highcharts.js"></script>
      <script src="../js/highcharts/code/modules/exporting.js"></script>

      <script type="text/javascript">

        $('#container').highcharts({
          colors: ['#F7B32B', '#E3170A', '#A9E5BB'],
          chart: {
            type: 'column'
          },
          title: {
          text: 'Rule Category Results September 2020'
          },
          subtitle: {
            text: 'Source: 119,287 higher education web pages from 151 universities using FAE Auditor'
          },
          legend: {
              reversed: true
          },
          xAxis: {
            categories: [
              'Midamerican',
              'No Conference',
              'Big Ten',
              'Ivy League',
              'Big East',
              'Atlantic 10',
              'Big 12',
              'Atlantic Coast',
              'Missouri Valley',
              'Pacific 12',
              'Southeast',
              'Big West',
              'Conference USA',
              'Western Athletic'
            ],
            crosshair: true
          },
          yAxis: {
            min: 0,
            max : 100,
            tickAmount: 6,
            title: {
              text: 'Percent Results'
            }
          },
          tooltip: {
            headerFormat: "&lt;span style='font-size:10px'>{point.key}&lt;/span>&lt;table>",
            pointFormat: '&lt;tr>&lt;td style="color:{series.color};padding:0">{series.name}: &lt;/td>&lt;td style="padding:0">&lt;b>{point.y:.1f} percent&lt;/b>&lt;/td>&lt;/tr>',
            footerFormat: '&lt;/table>',
            shared: true,
           useHTML: true
          },
          plotOptions: {
            series: {
                stacking: 'normal'
            },
            column: {
              pointPadding: 0,
              borderWidth: 0
            }
          },
          series: [{
            name: 'Manual Check',
            data: [46.6, 45.7, 47.2, 46.5, 48.3, 47.1, 48.2, 47.6, 47.8, 47.3, 47.4, 48.7, 48.4, 50.1]
            }, {
            name: 'Fail',
            data: [5.0, 4.0, 5.1, 6.0, 5.0, 6.4, 5.6, 6.6, 6.6, 7.3, 7.2, 6.0, 7.2, 6.4]
            }, {
            name: 'Pass',
            data: [48.4, 48.4, 47.7, 47.5, 46.8, 46.4, 46.1, 45.8, 45.6, 45.4, 45.4, 45.3, 44.4, 43.5]
            }]
        });
      </script>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      The chart in this slide shows the accessibility ranking for the athletic conferences used in thie evaluation based on the highest percentage of rules passed for all the web pages associated with that conference.

      The limitations of this evaluation were discussed in the previous slide.

      If you cannot see the chart or have difficulty reading charts there is an option to view a table of the data after the chart on the web page.

      The top conference this year was the Midamerican conference, followed by non-conference schools and the Big Ten.

    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Conclusions</title>
    <contents>
    <ul>
      <li>Human resources problem, more people need to understand accessibility.</li>
      <li>Communicate the importance of accessibility to vendors.</li>
      <li>Content creation and editing tools need to support accessible authoring.</li>
    </ul>

    <h2>Data is needed to help answer the following questions:</h2>
    <ul>
      <li>Current level of implementation of web accessibility in higher education?</li>
      <li>What accessibility requirements are understood and what requirements do people need to learn about?</li>
      <li>What development and procurement teams need to understand to improve accessibility?</li>
      <li>How are the tools students, faculty and staff use support creating accessible content?</li>
    </ul>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      The results show there is still much work to do to improve the accessibility and usability of web resources to people with disabilities in higher education.

      It is clear accessibility has a human resources problem.

      More people at our institutions need to know more about accessibility.

      People don't need to know everything about accessibility, but they need to know what is important for their job or role.

      Universities need to implement proactive plans to support the accessibility and usability of online administrative and instructional materials.

      An important part of those plans need to include procurement processes that encourage vendors to provide accessible web applications.

      To move web accessibility into the main stream of the campus culture authoring tools used to create online content need to support authors in learning about and including accessibility features in the online resources they create.

      Ask vendors how their products not only meet accessibility requirements, but also how they help students, faculty and staff learn about and create accessible content.


    </transcript>
  </slide>

  <slide>
    <title>Open Source Tools from Illinois</title>
    <contents>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/ainspector-wcag/">AInspector WCAG for Firefox</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://fae.disability.illinois.edu">Functional Accessibility Evaluator 2.1</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://accessibility-bookmarklets.org/">Public Bookmarklets Website</a></li>
      </ul>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      The links on this slide are to tools that use the same ruleset used in this evaluation.

      AInspector for Firefox is a extension for Firefox than analyzes the currently opened window in Firefox and generates a report shown in the left hand sidebar.

      The Functional Accessibility Evaluator or FAE is a server based tool to spider a website and provide in addition to page level reports a higher level rpoert on all the pages.

      The accessibility bookmarklets can be used on all modern browser to help visually highlight hidden accessibility information on web pages, which is very useful for manual inspection of a web page.

      These are open source tools, so they are free for you to use and share.

      Please contact me if you have any questions.
    </transcript>
  </slide>


  <slide>
    <title>Acknowledgments and Contact Information</title>
    <contents>
      <h2>Contact Information</h2>
      <div class="person">
        <p class="name">Jon Gunderson, Ph.D., CPWA</p>
        <p class="desc">Coordinator of Accessible IT Group</p>
        <p class="desc">Division of Disability Resources and Educational Services (DRES)</p>
        <p class="desc">College of Applied Health Sciences</p>
        <p class="desc">
          <a href="mailto:jongund@illinois.edu">jongund@illinois.edu</a>
        </p>
      </div>

      <h2>Acknowledgments</h2>
      <p>This work was carried out with the support of the University of Illinois, University of Illinois Foundation and an IBM corporate gift to support rule development.  I would also like to thank the Nicholas Hoyt (DRES) and Joshi Pramod (AITS).  A special thanks to the members of the OpenAjax Accessibility Task Force, the Open Accessibility Alliance Tools Discussion group and the many people who have taken time to provide feedback and report bugs on the tools or evaluation library.  Additional support is provided by the <a href="https://techsage.gatech.edu/">TechSAge</a> Project, which is funded by the National Institute on Disability, Independent Living, and Rehabilitation Research (NIDILRR grant number #90REGE0006-01-00 ).</p>
    </contents>
    <transcript>
      Please contact me if you have any questions about this presentation or the open source tools.

      This work was carried out with the support of the University of Illinois, University of Illinois Foundation and an IBM corporate gift to support rule development.

      I would also like to thank my colleagues Nicholas Hoyt of DRES and Joshi Pramod of AITS.
      A special thanks to the members of the OpenAjax Accessibility Task Force, the Open Accessibility Alliance Tools Discussion group and the many people who have taken time to provide feedback and report bugs on the tools or evaluation library.

      Additional support is provided by the TechSAge Project, which is funded by the National Institute on Disability, Independent Living, and Rehabilitation Research.
    </transcript>
  </slide>

</slides>
